You have to play the game. It's totally
irrational not to play the game.
>> This is John Myles White. He was a
director of engineering on PyTorch and
MSL, and since he quit recently, we
talked freely.
>> I feel like our goals should not be
written in a way where shipping the
thing we intended to leak is a success.
The general perception is the supply of
engineers is like way over supply.
>> We also talked about the incentives in
Big Tech.
>> You ran promotions in AI infra for a
long time.
>> You know, the only reason you do
anything is because there's a clear
story about how it's going to get you a
promotion.
>> You saw this, I saw this. What could you
do though?
Here's the full episode.
>> I'm curious if you're bullish on MSL
like after you were working there for a
bit and kind of seeing it from the
inside.
>> Oof, this is a I guess like a
a more radical question. I guess I will
be honest. Um
I am very bullish on Meta as a company
that I am now a stockholder of but not
an employee.
I am very bearish on Meta if you're an
employee who's not a stockholder,
uh which is turns out to not be really
anyone, but like you know, I think you
can think of yourself as mostly employee
if you're mostly getting cash and mostly
not equity. The more senior folks are
the ones who are more mostly stockholder
than employee.
Um
I and I think that's the the tension.
So, I do think like my sense is that
it's not unique where I don't get the
perception is unique to MSL. My
perception is that I think just
Meta as a place to be an employee is
less enjoyable than it used to be, but
it actually is being run very
effectively if what you care about is
the bottom line of the business. Uh and
so like I continue to invest in Meta and
I suspect I will continue to invest cuz
I do think it's actually from a business
perspective run quite well. But I do
think pretty uniformly, I think it's not
unique to MSL. I do think it's a much
more stressful time to be an employee
there than before.
>> What's the part that makes it or you're
saying employees might not uh enjoy
working there as much as they used to?
>> I I think that the I mean I think this
is true of all of Silicon Valley. So I
think in general like there was a a lot
of sense that like it was incredibly
easy to lose your good employees and so
you had to do everything impossible to
sacrifice to retain them. And you were
constantly constrained by an undersupply
of employees.
And I think basically everyone in
Silicon Valley's view, as far as I can
tell, is that that's mostly not true
outside of like a small set of like AI
researchers in frontier labs, where I
think people do still behave this way.
In fact, may behave this way more than
ever before.
But I think for everyone else, the
general perception is the supply of
engineers is like way oversupplied. And
especially I think actually people's
concern is with AI, maybe they're really
oversupplied.
I think
what happens is a new market dynamic,
which is like I think as an employer,
you're thinking, I don't actually have
to make some of these sacrifices to
acquire and retain talent. And so
therefore I'm going to make fewer of
them. And this can play out in a million
ways, but it can be like compensation,
but can also be things of like, do we do
things that upset the employees or do we
not? And how hesitant are we? Um how
much do we give them a voice and how
much do we not give them a voice? I
think that stuff has changed a lot in
the years I was at Meta.
Um
but my impression is Meta is not in any
way unique here. This is just a general
property of all of Silicon Valley. Um
but I do think, you know, as an
employee, I think it the the like the
labor supply and demand situation is
super different from when I started and
I think it is a thing that is going to
make generally being an employee
rougher, period.
>> It it feels like it can be subtle as
well. Like what you described of I guess
employees having less leverage, you
could see that affecting
um maybe even like reorg decisions or
things like that where it's like, you
know, if people leave, that is part of
the calculus of the reorg, and that is
less of a downside in now and maybe in
the future. So, I can see there being a
lot of downstream effects where
uh things just don't go as well for for
employees.
>> Oh, yeah. I mean, there's just so much
stuff that in the previous versions of
Meta was done that I think it was a bad
decision for the business, but made
sense from the context of retaining
talent.
Um you know, and I think that the
company is just doing less of that. From
the flip side, I mean, I guess to be
clear, I didn't say as I said before, I
do think for most people like
fundamentally just like the possibility
you might get laid off is the number one
emotional thing that causes people
stress.
And living in a world where you know
that is both happened recently and may
happen again in the future, I think sort
of like
is probably beats out all the other
questions of sort of lists and like food
and stuff. I think I think what prior to
the layoffs, when those things got taken
away, people freaked out and were like,
this is unforgivable. But then like once
they're like, oh, wait,
uh actually you guys might just fire me.
So, now I'm much more tolerant of you
taking away my food away.
Um
but I do think that like that that
fundamentally like it probably drives
for most people like the vast majority
of it. And actually I think for us with
this probably is one of the things that
makes say MSL more stressful than the
other frontier labs is the sense that it
might have layoffs.
In the sense that I think, you know, so
far there have been fewer rounds or at
least perceived to be fewer rounds than
some of the smaller startups like OpenAI
and Anthropic.
>> I I think another thing that is often
times used for retention is the promise
of growth or I guess career growth for
an employee. And, you know, I know you
you ran promotions in AI infra for a
long time. I was curious like if you saw
things change over the years.
>> I observed a lot of divisions of Meta
would really like stop talking about
like where your comp is, why you're
here, and you we pay you good money, and
you enjoy the work, and that's why you
stay. And a lot of people were like,
"No, the only reason you do anything is
because there's a clear story about how
it's going to get you a promotion."
And you would like, especially this is
really striking when I moved from data
infra, where it was one of the places I
was in earlier in infra, moving to AI
infra, and I was in AI infra for a while
before I came into sort of PyTorch part
of AI infra and then later ML.
One of the things that blew my mind is
that
there was not a single person I would
meet on any team in AI infra whose first
and foremost goal wasn't promotion.
This was a thing that sort of came up in
data infra, but was not like 90% of
people's attention. And when I started
at Meta, it was just like not ever a
thing. Uh actually, like you know, I
used to manage one of your previous
guests, Adrian, and like Adrian and I
were talked about career growth back in
the day, and one of the things that was
really amazing was like we started in
the sort of growth that actually had
never had anyone above IC7 ever in
history.
Um
on the sweet side, to be clear. There
were some other roles that had it, but
like um
at least this is what we were told. I
actually don't know for a fact it was
objectively true, but we were told this
by several people.
Um I think in that world, you just you
weren't focused on promotion, so it
wasn't a big thing. But then it became a
thing where it was like this is the
thing. Like you will one get more money,
more promoted, but also you'll have a
title that you can use for your next
job. And like everything is driven by
promotion dynamics. Um actually, I'd say
the org structure is by far most strong
in was monetization.
Um which is like when monetization would
hire people out of AI infra, it would
always literally be like, "Here is a
very detailed plan of work you will do
in order to get promoted." And that was
a thing that worked very effectively.
But it also, in my experience, like
wrecked tons of teams. Uh and I managed
a bunch of those teams and had to fix
them, but they were teams where like
basically everyone agreed the thing we
were working on was bad. No one thought
it would succeed, but people like, "Oh,
but I have to ship it because that's my
promo bar."
And you're getting to the state where
it's sort of just impossible to even
make good decisions about software
anymore because the promotions were so
important.
And then I think what happened as the
market became less pro-employee is that
people like, "Oh, no, no, no. You should
be afraid of being laid off. You should
not be worried about the positive chance
of a promotion." Um
but I don't know that that was a good I
don't think that was a good cultural
fix, but I do think it's been a bit of
like an attempt to undo some of the
damage from before, but I do think that
like sort of promotion mindset was
incredibly intense everywhere.
And and ironically it led to this thing
which I found really troubling, which
was
the thing that would actually let you
develop real skills that would do better
in your career going forward
increasingly got decoupled from the
promotions. You know, and I've seen a
lot of people on Twitter over the years
saying this, and I find it very
compelling, which is people like, "The
main thing that's wrong with the
engineering culture is that the big tech
companies is the promo culture." And I
really agree.
Uh, I actually think that ironically my
perception of this seems to be doing
better at this than many of other
companies that have even more formal
processes and more anonymous parties
involved.
But I do think that like
oh, what really matters is that you like
ran a rollout that affected 10 other
systems.
This causes people to like not build
clean systems, it causes them to build
systems that maximally are coupled to
the other systems in order to be able to
hit the promo bar. And that I think
actually you know, I met so many people
who didn't even like the work they were
doing because they're like, "Well, this
is what will get me promoted." Uh, and
so do you think that stuff was really
unfortunate? And especially I think
actually in the AI world it's been
especially unfortunate because it means
like
unless someone is clear how using the AI
tooling is going to get them promoted,
they may not do it, but it is without
doubt in my mind the only thing that's
going to matter for actual professional
development and growth and actually
being able to do more interesting work
in the future.
>> Yeah, I definitely saw some some unusual
behaviors, but we're all trying to play
the game because it helps people get
promoted and you retain people and all
that. So
>> Yeah, I mean unless your VP is ready to
fix that and totally shut it down, like
you have to play the game. It's totally
irrational not to play the game and I
think, you know, you either if you don't
want to be in that play, you have to
leave that work. If you're there, you've
got to play the game. You cannot be the
one who sort of unilaterally disarms,
but it is I mean it was it was
mind-blowing to me to see this culture I
think was unique to both monetization AI
infra, but it was
completely dominant in AI infra and it
was really it was not great for any
parties. And funny is it was like it
wasn't even good for the people who were
in it. Like they themselves had gotten
into this rat race that seemed to be
demoralizing to them.
>> You saw this, I saw this.
What what could you do though? I when I
was in it too, the people who were
talking about it, they were not
necessarily saying, "Yeah, this is this
is good." They were saying, "Yep, I'm
doing this I don't believe in, but we
both know that I need to do this for
this reason, so I'm doing it."
>> I think there are sort of two high
sources of uncertainty that compete and
I don't quite know how they balance out.
But I think one is like
I think people have a ton of agency in
choosing the culture of the team they
want to be on.
And if they're in a situation like that
and they don't love it, Meta has a lot
of teams that don't have that culture.
There are a lot of teams like PyTorch
was one of them where people were just
like genuinely in it for the love of the
craft.
And like people loved engineering as
engineering in PyTorch in a way that I
think was not present in a bunch of
other parts of Meta. I think people
wanted to come to PyTorch for that
reason and I think people came in and
were happy for that reason. So I do
think people just have agency in that
sense, which was like, "Yeah, within the
context of that machine, you got to
follow the rules, but it's not like
you're forced to be in that machine.
There were other rules.
Um not everyone would get them, and
maybe I choice is very choosy, but I
think many people could, and it was
worth doing.
I think the alternative that was also
was like
even within a team, managers can differ
a lot in how much they push on this.
And
I have personally been a person who I
think mostly benefited from actually
trying to bet on be on the stable team
that will gradually succeed over time
and will have a healthy culture and not
collapse and not do things like over
level ourselves.
But it does mean that you get promoted
slower, and this is where I think I I do
struggle with this a bit, which is I
think like
if you think at the end of the day what
you really want to do is do something
like compute your total sum of earnings
over your entire lifetime,
it maybe better to be in the orgs that
get promoted really fast and get fired
really fast. But there are a lot of
those orgs at Meta where people are
like, "Well, they're the stars. Oh,
actually no, it turns out they're
terrible in life to us, so we got rid of
all of them."
All of this happened a bunch of times in
the year
um
it might be that that is actually
economically rational. I'm not sure, but
certainly I think for myself about
emotionally rational and feeling like I
enjoy the craft of stuff, being on the
teams and PyTorch was like this. I mean,
one of the challenges actually PyTorch
had with hiring was actually the
perception that PyTorch held a higher
bar. People would be like, "Oh, I've
heard you guys are actually like much
tougher about promotions." And I'd be
like, "Yeah, honestly we are. Like
honestly, like our eights are like as
good as you're going to get anywhere in
this whole world. And you know, if you
want to be the best engineer you're ever
going to be in your entire life, you
should work with them. But like
our eights probably are better than the
tens in a couple of other teams.
Um if you want to be a ten, you maybe
should be in that team instead.
Uh and I think for some people that
would really turn them off, but I think
part of this was again really sort of
like agency and selection mechanism as I
think PyTorch selected people who
actually just loved engineering as
engineering. And then there were people
who were willing to tolerate slightly
fewer promotions. And then ironically
one interesting thing was that actually
there was that it became a bit of like a
um
magic thing that kind of turned out
well, which is because people perceived
PyTorch to hold such a higher bar. It
was much easier for us to convince
people outside of PyTorch that actually
our people were ready for eight or nine
or 10. Whereas other teams when they
tried to make this argument they're
like, "Oh, but you you guys are not
well-known and a high bar. Maybe you
guys are just overselling these people."
But in PyTorch people are like, "Oh,
yeah, like you you guys hired our guy
and thought he was pretty bad. So
actually we think you probably are
credible." Um and I think that that like
again, it's like in the short term
doesn't actually accumulate as fast, but
I think in the long term does have a ton
of benefits.
Whether it is the absolute like
compensation maximizing algorithm, I'm
not sure. And that's where I have a
little bit like torn torn. But for me I
was also like I was willing to
get 20% less compensation to be in a
place that I was more proud of.
>> Actually, that's funny because I
remember someone from PyTorch would join
one of our collaborations for instance.
You know, someone would join and go,
"Oh, he's a five, but really he's like a
seven. Like he's he's better than all of
our engineers, but we don't know why
he's a five, but he's a five." And that
was not uncommon working with that org.
>> Yeah, I mean I mean again, this is like
I mean it would it would come out like
flat out in like opportunity chats where
we tried to hire someone. And then
they're like, "Hey, you know, PyTorch is
cool, but like aren't you guys like
really under-leveled?" That would be
like the first question people would ask
and have to be like,
"Maybe or maybe we're holding the right
levels. Uh you know, you got to decide
where you want to take a chance on us."
But you know, but I think the flip side
is, you know, that you know, we really
did train people. Like a lot of people
who were in PyTorch really learned to be
remarkably good.
>> I know before PyTorch you you worked on
some of the data and experimentation
tools at Meta. How was that org and like
how was your experience growing in in
early Facebook before all this promo
craziness?
>> Well, I came into
wild ride,
which was actually honestly an amazing
experience. And you know, some of my
happiest years of my life were like my
first 2 years at Meta, but also some of
the most fearsome and scary over years
were also there. But like I'm I joined
the team that I signed up for, and when
I signed up it was supposed to be called
data science.
Before I arrived cuz I asked for a
6-month leave to work on Julia, the
programming language I was one of the
core contributors to.
I asked for a 6-month leave between
finishing grad school and going to
Facebook at that time.
And during that 6-month period, the guy
who hired me quit.
And then the team that was called data
science that I was hired into got split
into two teams, one called core data
science and one called data science
infrastructure.
And then
that itself drove became really tricky
because I wanted to join core data
science, but really loving collaborating
with the data science infrastructure
people who were the ones who owned the
experimentation tools.
Um
working in the experimentation tools was
like honestly like I think to this day
the most most people who know me from
Meta are like, "Oh yeah, John was really
helpful for that stuff." I actually
think like almost nothing I worked on as
an IC ever went anywhere close to being
as valuable to the business as the
experimentation stuff.
Um
and I don't think I was ever as good at
any of the other stuff. I really loved
being in that space, and I think it was
like really influential to the business.
Um
that said, I was on this core data
science team that was like an insane
ball of stress. You know, I joined, it
would be radically reworked, it had new
managers. I actually wound up really
liking the new managers, but that was
still a source of churn.
But then a few months into it, someone
who actually was on the data science
infrastructure team, which is
particularly what's amusing, but
attributed his team to being core data
science
because he perceived that there was sort
of the team he really was on when he
wrote this paper, published this paper
um,
the Proceedings of the National Academy
of Science, called something like
Emotional Contagion in Social Networks,
um,
that wound up just becoming like the
absolute singular worst piece of PR for
Meta as a business that year. Um,
just absolute disaster. I mean, I was
like really, really trying to prevent
this from happening, but I didn't have
the authority to prevent it. But, like,
you know, at least people perceived I
was on the side who was not happy with
this decision. Um, but then Meta that I
was, you know, was on the team
where I was doing the data science
infrastructure work, that's sort of very
inward-facing and very safe, but I was
affiliated with a more researchy
division that was publishing these
papers that went from becoming sort of a
PR win to a PR nightmare very rapidly.
Um, and that team, I think, was one of
the most my formative experiences at
Meta because it really was like,
"Well, what happens if this team just
gets fully disbanded?" And this was like
in a in a world where there weren't
layoffs. It was like, "Well, Meta
doesn't do layoffs, but this team maybe
has got itself to a state where it's
going to get laid off." Um, you know,
and the guy who wrote this paper wound
up having to do like a company-wide Q&A
where, effectively, he sort of just
apologized to the entire business as his
Q&A. Um,
it was really just like a mind-blowing
experience. And it was actually it was
like one where it's like, you know, I
came in as an IC4, and all of a sudden
we were like in these meetings where,
like, you know, the head of legal being
like, "Well, why did you guys do this?"
Uh, and, you know, having to have these
discussions with them on a regular
basis, and really trying to figure
through like what was the future of our
team. Um, but it was great. Um, that
blew over, for what it's worth, and then
I spent several years just working on
our experimentation tools, you know, I
was like one of the main developers of,
uh, Deltoid 3, which is I think now just
called Deltoid cuz I think it's been
Deltoid for so long they just refer to
it as Deltoid. Um, but at one point it
was like the third iteration. Um, and I
worked a ton on that. And then,
especially, it was a really simple of
how career growth can actually happen,
which is like,
I was on the team, and then all of a
sudden almost all of the senior
engineers left the team in the span of
like 6 months. And then I went from
being like at the point maybe I was
already an IC5 when they all left, I'm
not sure, but I went from being like one
of the people on the team building
experimentation tools to the only one
who remembered how anything worked left.
And suddenly I went from being sort of
random IC5 to like de facto TL for a
bunch of stuff. Um which was actually an
amazing opportunity for growth and I
think people understate how often these
things can happen in tech. Um but it
meant that I wound up like really being
like able to drive a bunch of the vision
for the AB testing tools for years,
which were you know hugely successful at
Meta. Um and it really was like
some of the most fulfilling work I ever
did at Meta.
>> And just to give people context, Deltoid
is the AB testing framework or the thing
that you opt in, you know, one code path
to A, one code path to B, and you
measure all the the downstream benefits
of ideally your test, right?
>> Yeah, I mean
I I think one of the things that's like
so kind of mind-blowing to me is like
you actually do one of these decisions
where maybe I did make bad career
decisions, which is like uh as far as I
can tell every time I've ever looked at
it, the Statsig product, which I now
don't know what its state is after they
got bought by OpenAI, is just like is
Deltoid. Uh this is one of the things
where like you know, stuff in Meta, when
you've been at Meta, you work on these
things like I also know that DataSwarm.
And when people are like what's
DataSwarm? Like it is literally Airflow.
And it's not like metaphorically
Airflow, like the guy who wrote Airflow
built DataSwarm, quit, and like a week
later open-sourced Airflow.
Uh and you know, and Deltoid is like not
quite the same cuz it's not the same
people left and built Statsig, but my
perception is that for most people who
will be watching this, if they've ever
seen Statsig, my perception is that like
almost the entire UI is the same, almost
all the functionality is the same.
Um this is one of these things where I
like you know, probably should have
built this Deltoid startup many years
earlier and like did not have the wisdom
to do that.
>> I think there is another one called
Optimizely as well. Yeah, so
I've I've seen many companies. It seems
like a very repeatable playbook where
you just take something that people take
for granted that's state-of-the-art from
a big tech company, and you just give it
to everyone in the industry, and it
actually creates like a billion-dollar
companies pretty I it's it's hard, but
at least the product market fit and idea
part are relatively solved since it's
creating so much value for these big
companies. For this podcast, I produce
transcripts for every episode for
convenient skimming, and I built a
custom tool to automate that.
Recently, I noticed in the Barbara
Liskov transcript, my simple
speech-to-text tool was getting a lot of
things wrong. For instance, the CLU
programming language is spelled all caps
c l u, not clue.
So, to fix this, I used Cursor 3, picked
the strongest version of Opus 4.7 extra
high, and had an agent make a plan to
fix that. And while I was waiting, I
figured I'd trigger a few more agents
for code cleanups and front-end
improvements.
Um it generated a reasonable plan with
rich system diagrams. It applied all the
changes within minutes, and worked on
the first try.
So, if you want to build something with
the flexibility of sending off a bunch
of agents with frontier models of your
choice, you can go to cursor.com to try
out Cursor 3.
You know, I saw before you worked at
Meta, you were working on the Julia
programming language, and I actually
wasn't familiar about it. So, I I read
into it a little bit, and looks like it
was part of these data science language
wars, basically, where there was R
versus Julia versus Python. What is
Julia, and what what is the context on
that war there?
>> Yeah, well, certainly, I think I made it
more of a part of the war. I don't think
it had to necessarily be part of it. Uh
although, I do think also, like, the
simple fact of the reality is, like,
programming languages are products, and
products exist in an ecosystem where
they're in zero-sum competition, and
claiming claiming that they're not in
zero-sum competition is like a very cute
thing people say is appropriate, but
it's clearly false and I think just
makes everyone worse by misleading them.
Um but like um
I mean so Julia for me and it's actually
sort of why did Julia so so appealing? I
mean
for me what Julia's pitch was like we
should be able to write code in a
high-level language that looks like
Python or like MATLAB, which is really
the language it was originally designed
to destroy. It was really designed to
get rid of MATLAB. Uh it was made by MIT
math people who wanted to get rid of
MATLAB. Um and it really like targeted
that market much more than data science.
It started in the sort of I think I was
involved in pushing it towards data
science. But you know, to me the thing I
would do when I give talks about Julia
if you're like, "Listen, let's look at
the R function for distance like compute
a distance matrix between a bunch of
vectors." So you're like, you know,
pairs of vectors and you get all the
distance matrix.
Um
if you look at the like that function
and then you actually try to figure out
how it's implemented in R, what you find
is like C code that is a very reasonable
C code that is just a bunch of for loops
like you know, loop through all the rows
and all the columns and then compute the
distance at that row and you're done.
If you basically take that code verbatim
and just trans like translate it naively
into R,
you're going to take some type
information away. You're going to get
rid of some like ints and float
signatures, but otherwise you're going
to basically write for loops that look
exactly the same.
The R code is going to be like somewhere
between 1,000 to 10,000 times slower
than C.
And this to me was the thing that just
like drove me insane when I'm just like,
wait, what? Like these two programs are
like 80% the same.
Why is one not as fast? And Julia really
was all about this notion that like that
was unacceptable. And that's what made
it so appealing when the first pound
like the first post by the original
founders went out. I was like, "Oh, you
guys are doing the thing I wanted people
to do." Which is like
not claim that it is impossible to make
high-level languages fast.
Which is like so much of actually how
the Python R community sometimes behave
is to be like, "Oh, well,
we can't be fast, but also fast isn't
important." And to me, like that that
double hit of like, "Well, we can't be
it, and it's not important." really
didn't work for me. So, Julia really
resonated. I think I probably as the
guilty party of trying to make it more
part of the data science world is cuz I
was myself a heavy user of R and was
just so disappointed in R. Um just so
incredibly disappointed in how often I
would try to do a project and R just
like fought me at every step of the way.
Um
but Python is also like this. I mean, if
you look at all the really great
libraries like PyTorch, like, you know,
deep down at the end of the day, you're
going to look at C++ code or maybe even
looking at like handwritten assembly or
handwritten like kernels for GPUs.
Um or at least you're looking at
something written in a much lower-level
language. Um and so, Julia was really
like about trying to solve that. And I
don't think it totally won, which I
think is probably why you didn't know
about it. I think it was very hip at one
point and has become less hip, but it's
actually doing okay. Like it's I think
it's in the top 25 programming languages
by users in the world. So, I think it's
a
real a real language
um that's really out there.
But for me, the thing that really
matters, even though I don't know that
it's killing it, Julia is like the only
people still actually fighting that
fight.
>> What's the intuition behind why R is
10,000 times slower when the code is,
you know, the symbols are relatively
similar to the C?
>> Fundamentally, any code that is slow is
slow cuz it's doing stuff it doesn't
need to do. Like that's just sort of the
most basic fact about slow code is that
the reason you're slow is cuz you could
have done something else and you did
something slower instead. And something
like R is doing this pretty easy. It's
in Python. It's not quite as dire, but
it's still there is
you wind up paying an enormous amount of
overhead cost for the possibility that
someone might do something more dynamic.
And because they might do it. And to
give you an example, which is really
astonishing about R is in R for instance
the brace that you use to ins- to find a
block is an operator that can be
overridden and the user can redefine.
So they can make braces mean something
else. But so that means when you see a
brace in code, you can't just be like, I
know what this is, I can move on. You
have to be like, no, I need to look up
and check did the user redefine this?
Um
I think it I think it's brace and not
parenthesis, but it's been a while, so I
haven't double checked. But it may also
be parenthesis or it's possible I
flipped them. We can like, you know,
check offline and see whether my memory
is good. But like you just wind up with
so much stuff like this that is so like
maybe changed and you don't know whether
it changed, so you need to go check
whether it changed. And the checks are
very expensive, especially if you're
doing something like adding two 60-bit
64-bit integers. That's like one machine
cycle, like it is one machine cycle. But
a check like does addition still mean
whatever I think it is could be hundreds
to thousands of machine cycles. And so
you wind up like swapping in things that
are very inefficient.
Places that you don't need. And this is
particularly R is amazing like there's
this amazing paper
by a couple of students uh and a a
senior professor named Jan Vitek, but
it's about the design uh called
something like uh evaluating design of
the R programming language.
And one of the things they look at is
like especially R has an especially
tricky thing, which is unlike Python, R
is also a lazily evaluated language,
where the arguments to functions are not
evaluated before you start the function
body. They wait until the function kicks
off and they just are passed as promise
objects.
And what they look at is they look at
like, well, how often are these promises
could have been effect like eagerly
evaluated? And how often is the overhead
of these promises worth it? And their
conclusion is like 70% or maybe more,
maybe it's 90%. I forget the numbers.
You basically have no reason you needed
to do this. Like almost never do you
need this.
But, you actually pay like an enormous
overhead cost for having agreed to do
this. Um and a good example I say in
Python also is like
in Python
you can like manipulate the symbol table
using using functions in the inspect
module.
And so, what that means is like you can
never be sure of what something's bound
to. You always have to be afraid and
check.
Um and just sort of general the lack of
invariants that like that's what makes a
language fast. It's like you have a lots
of invariants. What makes your language
slow is you have lots of stuff you might
have to go confirm at runtime.
And R is just incredibly pervasively
like this.
>> I looked at some of your popular past
tweets and I thought maybe we could
discuss some of them. So, one of them
this is the most popular tweet that I
think you ever wrote. And you you said
that you're continually continually
disappointed by how many grad students
and postdocs get the impression that
industry is a safe position of last
resort that they can always fall back on
if things sour in their academic
careers. And
I thought that was interesting because I
thought the
I thought the opposite was also very
commonly true where people might you
know, want to avoid industry so they go
and get higher education. So, I'm
curious your you know, your thought on
this and what what made you think this.
>> Really what drove me nuts was there were
just a ton of people
who fundamentally wanted to be
professors or postdocs and were in a PhD
program.
And they were like, "Well, if I fail
out, I'll go into industry."
Um
and this like
one is that you would interact with
people during interviews who like
clearly didn't want to be there. Just
like so unambiguously did not want to be
there and clearly viewed this as like a
failure that they were interviewing.
And you're like, "Well, that's not
really like a positive sign that we want
to hire someone who like doesn't seem
like they're going to enjoy the job.
But
in addition a bunch of people, and this
is what drove me so insane cuz I think
it's like all parties involved in the
academic system hurt students doing
this,
is that like
so many people just assume that when
they finally decided to get industry
position, it was going to be trivial.
And then they didn't find it trivial. I
think a lot of academic people were
like, well, smart people are in academia
and the dumb people are in industry. So,
if I need to go compete with the dumb
people, it will be easy.
Um and I think there was a lot of that.
Um you know, there was a person who was
I'll give you an example. There was a
person who was like effectively a CS
professor who I interviewed.
And this person like could not figure
out how to pass a values between the
various functions that they were calling
in the interview. Like literally they
were like, what I would do is I would
call this function and it would print
out in the REPL, and then I would read
it as a human, and then I would go like
type it into this other piece of code.
And I was like, oh, you you are better
programming than this, right? Cuz like
you're a professor of computer science.
And they're like, no, no, this is how I
work. And I was like, well,
this is not going to set you up for
success if we actually have to get you
writing code in prod here.
>> I saw a few other popular tweets that
you had. They were about um
like favorite statistics papers and
favorite recommendations of statistical
books that you're saying, oh, everyone's
got to read these.
How come you have such strong
recommendations on statistical uh
literature? And then also, what are
those recommendations?
>> I love statistics. I think I'll never
not love it, but I think it's the
craziest and what I mean by craziest
it's a field that fundamentally sells
people the idea that they can use
statistical methods in real life.
But in reality, what they do is do pure
mathematics and study how statistical
methods work in a idealized theoretical
world.
And
in pure math, like you know, as an
undergraduate I did pure math and I
loved things like number theory. In pure
math, it's just you just pure, it's
pure. You prove it, it's internally
coherent, there's no attempt to like
reconcile with reality. Reality doesn't
even matter. You just like there's a
rules, we follow the rules, we're in
this internally consistent system.
And then in super applied fields like
software engineering, you're just like,
well, the thing runs. Like the code
runs. I don't I don't know what to tell
you. Like I can't prove this code runs,
but like we ran it in prod and it had
like eight nines of reliability, which
makes it better than like most of the
software ever written by humans.
We're good. Um statistics is this super
crazy field where you reason in the
mathematics, but then make all these
claims about how it's going to be useful
to people in practice. And this I think
is where where opinions come in so
strongly is that I think some people
just like are very, very honest and hold
themselves to a super high bar.
And some people I think are super
cavalier about stuff. And they're like
roughly just like, well, I said it was
true. And then you're like, well, is it
true? And they're like,
uh and you're like, let's really dig
into the proof. And they're like, fine.
You know, one of the four people I love,
love, love, love more than anybody is
Larry Wasserman.
I've never met the guy.
Uh so I don't know what he's like as a
human, but like his books are like to me
the embodiment of like hyper intense
honesty. He just seems like a good
person just like, I cannot tell a lie.
And just like therefore like everything
you get from Wasserman is exactly true.
Like he tells you exactly what he's
assuming. He tells you exactly what's
implied. And he's also extremely clear
about being like, I actually don't claim
these other things that you might want
me to claim because they're not true. Um
and I think a ton of statistics books
are not like that. Ton of statistics are
like, use our methods, they're great. Um
and so I think Wasserman is really at
the at the top.
Another book that someone recommended to
me sort of halfway through my career, a
method that I loved, um I think it's
called something like introduction to
agnostic statistics. Uh it's a book by a
guy named Peter Eranell. And he's I
think another person like this who just
like
incredibly concerned with whether the
things he says are true or false and
he's hyper rigorous and hyper careful.
And again, I think a lot of people in
statistics are not hyper rigorous and
hyper careful, so I love the book.
And so the recommendations I gave,
Wasserman, like literally anything you
can get by Larry Wasserman, buy and
read. If you want to learn statistics,
like I don't think any book has ever
been better than the books he's written
in my entire life. I've never seen
anything come close to being as good.
The Peter Arena book, I think is
probably as good as like a thing you
could be ever reading if you're like a
social scientist or someone working more
practically. It's a little less math
heavy than the Wasserman books.
>> And I think there is a lot of um
value in big technology and
understanding some statistics or doing
it rigorously because I've been in so
many AV test review meetings and I think
a lot of people who kind of just enter
the industry and you know, they they see
the UI and they go, I got a green bar
here. Please give me the approval to
ship my my code path. Um but actually if
you kind of dig in and you ask some
whys, you're like, wait, there was it
was red yesterday. Why is it you know,
what's going on here?
Uh the the understanding is very
superficial and people are just trying
to they're just trying to move forward
whether or not it's actually
statistically, you know, beneficial
across the user base, so
>> I mean that's a good I mean ironically
it's a great example of sort of
everything we talked about today summed
up. It's like a story I have when we're
trying to get Delta 3 to ship out. You
know, at that point Delta 1 was still
the default. And there was a person who
came to us and this person was actually
like otherwise great and I loved
interacting with them. But this
interaction was really I was like,
"Woof, this reflects a lot of cultural
pathology of our company." And what
they're like, "Hey,
I can't let you ship Delta 3." And I'm
like, "Why? Why can't Why can't we ship
it?" And they're like,
"Well, our holdout goes from being
statistically significant win for the
company to being not statistically
significant in Delta 3.
And I think it's a regression." And I
was like,
"All right, it might be a regression,
but maybe it's also the truth." They're
like, "I actually don't know which it
is, but you guys are going to wait until
the half is over and we've decided we
hit our goal, and then you can ship till
go 3."
And I was like, "Oh, but wait." I was
like, "Your your win is so close to the
border between you did nothing and won
that literally like mild tweaks in our
code have turned it off." I'm like, "I
feel like that's not a win people would
be so concerned about, and especially
this notion that like you're almost
significant, so therefore you failed, or
you're just barely not significant, you
know, you win or you fail." That I think
is this is super dangerous culture. I
mean, one of the worst things I ever saw
was a team that I managed was squeeze,
and one of the things they told me was
they're like, "Hey, you know, we have to
do this thing cuz we made a goal." And I
was like, "Okay, but what are you going
to do next half?" They're like, "Oh,
definitely July 2nd we're going to
delete this code."
And I was like, "Wait, then why are we
shipping it?" They're like, "Well, cuz
we can't miss our goals." And I was
like, "I feel like our goals should not
be written in a way where shipping the
thing we intend to delete literally a
day later is a success." And they're
like, "Yeah, that's fair." And I was
like, "What do you mean fair? Come on,
man. Like, don't do this." And
eventually, you know, I convinced them
not to do it. I was like, "I'm the
manager. I can decide the ratings. We
don't have to just like do this." But
people really like firmly believe this.
And I think the statistics thing with
the problem is like
a lack of understanding of statistics
leads into other weird pathologies of
how people are evaluated. And the two
together become like extra dangerous.
>> Coming to an end, just like a few
questions kind of like reflecting on
your career so far.
Do you have a regret that maybe other
people could learn from?
>> Oh, yeah. People ask me this so much as
I went through the years, especially as
I became like a more senior manager and
then a director, but I like, you know,
have a canned answer cuz I've been asked
this a million times.
I for uh like my first several years had
Javi as my skip.
For people who don't know him, he's
currently I think the COO of NetApp, but
you know, he was first the head of
growth and then the head of growth and
ads and then I think now he runs like
roughly 50% of NetApp.
But like Javi was my skip and every time
my actual manager, this guy named Danny,
would be like, "Javi wants people to
come to his office hours. No one shows
up and he feels like it's a waste of his
time. Someone should go." And I
basically just there was like, "Well, I
don't have anything like actually that
valuable to say to Javi, so I'm just
going to waste his time and I don't want
to be the person who wastes his time, so
I never went." And I look back and I'm
like
cuz especially as I started running
office hours as I had a larger org where
I couldn't do like one-on-ones with
everyone and had to do office hours and
people wouldn't go and I was like
"Man, I wish people would come to my
office hours." And like I Javi was also
feeling this way and he's like, "Man,
I wish I would I would give anything for
one of these people to show up." But
like I just never showed up and I look
back and I'm like, "First of all, this
was an amazing opportunity that I
wasted. But in addition, it's not just
that I wasted it for myself, I also
probably just like made his life worse
off by not actually getting him to be
able to take advantage of this thing he
was offering us." And so I was like,
"This is a decision that basically
harmed both parties that I did out of
fear." Um
I'm sure there's probably a million
other examples of me doing this that are
not as clear in my head, but this is one
where like, you know, Danny probably
came to like our team once a week and
told us to show sign up and no one ever
did.
Um and I think of this every time where
I'm like "Listen, if like you know
something important about the future of
this org or this team or even if you
just like honestly have any questions at
all, if you have a leader who's showing
up and saying, 'I want to hear from you
folks,' go. Um I think especially like
if you're a more junior IC watching
this, like I think it is hard to
understand how painful it is at director
and above to actually know what it's
like on the ground. You're just like so
removed from being an IC3 and IC4
anymore, just so removed. And not just
from their place in life, but also like
what's happening to them, what's true in
the code base, what the team dynamics
are. You know, like you know, there were
points where I had like a manager
managing managers managing managers. You
know, there's just so much indirection.
I think people way, way should more
often, if a leader says like, "Please
show up and talk to me." do it. Um you
know, if someone sees like you come and
say something weird, you know, that can
be bad. So, you don't show up and be
like, "I want you to tell me how to get
promoted."
Uh it's probably like not your greatest
first conversation, but if you're like,
"Hey, I think this part of our org could
be better. Could you help me?"
Leaders love that. That's what they
want. And like so many people are afraid
to do it. And I think it basically makes
all parties worse off.
>> And then last question for you, with all
the experience that you have now, if you
could go back to the beginning of your
career and give yourself some advice,
what would you say?
>> It's tricky because I think I am a
person with very strong opinions, but I
also think I can be more self-conscious
than I should. And do you think they're
like
have more confidence that you can do
bigger stuff.
And that as long as you hold yourself to
a high level of discipline, the bigger
stuff is really possible.
I think like when I was younger, you
know, basically at every step of the
way, like from high school student to
college student all the way, I think I
tended to
way too often like cast doubt about what
I could do.
Um and I think you know, that is the
single like biggest set of mistakes I've
made. It's just this repeated pattern of
like not being ambitious enough or not
believing something was tractable. And I
think I've gotten a lot better. That's
you know, why I don't like the defeatism
in other programming language
communities. But like um
I think it for me is like this thing
that sort of I think you know, really
could have been better. And I think it's
true for a lot of people. I think I just
a lot of people like
they
they over convince themselves of the
greatness of other people and under
convince themselves of how much they can
achieve and that combination means that
they just like way less try to do risky
things than they could have. And then I
think they like especially I think until
we interacted enough people who have
succeeded I think it's hard to realize
like how often they're like not actually
doing that much better than you. They
just tried and you didn't try.
Um so I think that is probably like you
know the the biggest thing that if I
could go back and tell like a
20-year-old me
um probably is that.
>> Thank you so much for your time. I I
really appreciate it, John.
>> It's been a real pleasure and thanks for
having me.
>> Thank you for listening to the podcast.
It's a passion project of mine that I
really enjoyed building. Another passion
project that I've been working on kind
of in secret is building an ergonomic
keyboard that I wish existed and I
finally have a prototype so I'd love to
show you what we've built. It's ultra
low profile and ergonomic and I couldn't
find anything like it on the market so
that's why we built it. I'll put a link
to the keyboard in the description. You
can take a look and learn more about the
project there. We could definitely use
your support. Also, if you have any
feedback for me about the show, I'd love
to hear it. Comments on YouTube have led
to guests coming on like Ilya Grigoric
and David Fowler. I wasn't aware of them
until someone dropped a comment. Also
feedback in the comments helped me learn
to reduce the number of cliffhangers in
the intros. So your comments definitely
make a difference. Please keep letting
me know what you'd like to see more of
in the show and I'll see you in the next
episode.